We now have a fresh GitHub repo and
can add files and
make changes to those files and
Git will track it for us.
As I've said before, GitHub is built upon
the version control system called Git.
Version control systems let you record
the history of all the changes you make
to a project so you can go back to
earlier versions if you make a mistake.
In Git,
a record of a change is called a commit.
Generally anytime you make a small but
significant change to your project files,
you'll record that change, or commit it.
Let's make a change to a file and
commit it.
I'll click open this repository
to locate my repository.
Then open the project in a text editor.
I'll go to the README file, delete this
line and type it in a nicer format.
Then I'll save and
go back to GitHub desktop.
On the left, in the Changes tab,
you'll see a list of all the files that
have been changed since the last commit.
As well as the individual changes
that were made on the right.
Deletions are highlighted in red and
additions are highlighted in green.
In the history tab, you'll see a list of
all the commits you've made to a project.
The files that were changed as part
of the commit, and the additions and
deletions that were made to those files.
Click back to the Changes tab and you can
see now that there's one changed file.
To commit this change, I'll add a commit
message here where it says summary.
The commit message should be a succinct
summary of the changes I've made since my
last commit.
In this case I'll type updated
title of README file.
Then I'll click commit to master.
Let's check our work on github.com.
You can actually open the file and
view it here.
As you can see,
my change hasn't been made yet.
That's because I need to go back to
GitHub desktop and click Push origin.
This will make sure that the latest
version of the repo that I have stored
locally on my computer, matches
the version that exists on GitHub.com.
Now I can go back to GitHub.com,
refresh, and view my changes.
Let's add a couple of files to this repo.
For example, say I wanted to add
some Techdegree starter files.
I can go to my Techdegree home page,
download the starter files,
unzip this and move the contents of this
folder into my Techdegree project folder.
Now I can go back to GitHub Desktop,
and I can see I have two changed files, or
the files I added here on the left.
To commit these changes and put them
on GitHub, I can add a commit message.
This time I'll put added
project starter files.
And I can also add a link to your
description if I want to but
that's optional and
click, commit to master.
Then I'll click, Push origin.
Now if I go back to github.com, refresh,
I can see all of the new
files I just added.
If you ever go to GitHub and
don't see your changes,
double check and make sure you've
included a commit message,
committed to master and
clicked push to origin.
You wanna make sure that any unsaved
changes have been committed and synced with
your GitHub repo, before you submit
your Techdegree projects for grading,
because your Techdegree project reviewer
won't be able to see any changes you make
after you submit.
Every time you update
the project on your computer,
you'll commit changes and
sync them with GitHub.
It's as easy as that.
Now you're ready to start
submitting Techdegree projects and
building up a portfolio of work on GitHub.
What if you already have a completed or
partially completed project that you wanna
make into a repository and
put onto GitHub?
As I said in a previous video,
creating your repo first is a good
habit to get into and I recommend it.
But sometimes you'll need to do it this
way because you forgot to create a repo or
starting with some starter files,
things like that.
Here I have a Techdegree project
that I've been working on.
To add this project to
GitHub Desktop as a repository,
go to GitHub Desktop and
choose File> New Repository.
The New Repository window will pop up.
Now this is very important.
If you're turning an existing
project folder into a Git repository,
the repository name must exactly match
the name of your project folder.
And here where it says Local Path,
the path should point to the parent
folder where your project folder lives.
In my case the parent folder
is that folder called Code,
that houses all of my
Techdegree projects.
So I'll give this the name
techdegree-project-4.
And for now the description will
be this is Techdegree Project 4.
This project has some JavaScript in it.
So I'll choose the Node option for
the Git ignore file.
And I'll click Create Repository.
Notice this drop down menu shows
us a list of all our repositories.
Here's the project we just added, but
it's listed in the other category
instead of the GitHub category.
That's because we haven't
published it to GitHub yet.
To publish, click Publish Repository,
unclick keep this code private,
and click Publish Repository.
Now go to github.com,
and you'll see the folder and
all of its files are now on GitHub.
We can now make changes, and add,
and delete files all we want,
as well as make commits and
push those commits to GitHub.
If you're interested in looking
into Git and GitHub a little more,
check out the teacher's notes for
other Treehouse courses and
workshops that cover them in more depth.
There's a lot more you can do with GitHub,
but
it all begins with publishing your
project to a GitHub repository.
Thanks for watching, and
have fun sharing your code.